<section id="examples">
    <title>Examples and Usage</title>
    <para>
      Some examples of Rivet usage follow.  Some prior Tcl knowledge
      is assumed.  If you don't know much Tcl, don't worry, it's easy,
      and there are some good resources available on the web that will
      get you up to speed quickly.  Go to the 
      <link linkend="websites">web sites</link> section and have a look.
    </para>

    <example id="hello world">
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <para>
			As with any tool, it's always nice to see something work, so
			let's create a small "Hello World" page.
		</para>
      <para>
			Assuming you have Apache configured correctly, create a file
			called <filename>hello.rvt</filename> where Apache can find
			it, with the following content:
      </para>
      <programlisting>&hello.rvt;</programlisting>
      <para>
			If you then access it with your browser, you should see a
			blank page with the text "Hello World" (without the quotes) on it.
      </para>
    </example>

    <example>
		<title>Generate a Table</title>
	  	<para>
	   	In another simple example, we dynamically generate a table:
	  	</para>
	  	<programlisting>&table.rvt;</programlisting>
	  	<para>
	    	If you read the code, you can see that this is pure Tcl.  We
	    	could take the same code, run it outside of Rivet, and it
	    	would generate the same HTML!
	  	</para>
	  	<para>
	    	The result should look something like this:
	  	</para>
	  	<graphic fileref="images/table.png"/>
    </example>

    <example id="variable_access">
      <title>Variable Access</title>
      <para>
			Here, we demonstrate how to access variables set by GET or
			POST operations.
      </para>
      <para>
			Given an HTML form like the following:
      </para>
      <programlisting>&vars.html;</programlisting>
      <para>
			We can use this Rivet script to get the variable values:
      </para>
      <programlisting>&vars.rvt;</programlisting>
      <para>
			The first statement checks to make sure that the
			<varname>boss</varname> variable has been passed to the
			script, and then does something with that information.  If
			it's not present, an error is added to the list of errors.
      </para>
      <para>
	In the second block of code, the variable
	<varname>salary</varname> is fetched, with one more error
	check - because it's a number, it needs to be composed of
	digits.
      </para>
      <para>
	The <varname>boss</varname> variable isn't required to have
	been sent - we set it to "Mr. Burns" if it isn't among the
	information we received.
      </para>
      <para>
	The last bit of variable handing code is a bit trickier.
	Because <varname>skills</varname> is a listbox, and can
	potentially have multiple values, we opt to receive them as a
	list, so that at some point, we could iterate over them.
      </para>
      <para>
	The script then checks to make sure that
	<varname>errlist</varname> is empty and outputting a thankyou
	message.  If <varname>errlist</varname> is not empty, the list
	of errors it contains is printed.
      </para>
    </example>
    
    <example id="file_upload">
      <title>File Upload</title>
      <para>
			The <command>::rivet::upload</command> command endows Rivet with an
			interface to access files transferred over http as parts of a
			multipart form.  The following HTML in one file, say,
			<filename>upload.html</filename> creates a form with a text
			input entry. By clicking the file chooser button the file
			browser shows up and the user selects the file to be uploaded
			(the file path will appear in the text input).  In order to make
			sure you're uploading the whole file you must combine the
			action of the enctype and method attributes of the
			&lt;form...&gt; tag in the way shown in the example.  Failure
			to do so would result in the client sending only the file's
			path, rather than the actual contents.
      </para>
      <programlisting>&upload.html;</programlisting>
      <para>
			In the script invoked by the form
			(<filename>upload.rvt</filename>) <command>upload</command>
			<arg>argument ...</arg> commands can be used to manipulate the
			various files uploaded.
      </para>
      <programlisting>&upload.rvt;</programlisting>
      <para>
			Don't forget that the apache server must have write access to
			the directory where files are being created.  The Rivet Apache
			directives have a substantial impact on the upload process,
			you have to carefully read the docs in order to set the
			appropriate directives values that would match your
			requirements.
      </para>
      <para>
			It is also important to understand that some 
			<command>upload</command> commands are effective only when
			used in a mutually exclusive way.  Apache stores the data in
			temporary files which are read by the <command>upload save
			<arg>upload name</arg><arg>filename</arg></command> or by the
			<command>upload data <arg>upload name</arg></command>
			command. Subsequent calls to these 2 commands using the same
			<arg>upload name</arg> argument will return no data on the
			second call.  Likewise <command>upload channel <arg>upload
			name</arg></command> will return a Tcl file channel that you
			can use in regular Tcl scripts only if you haven't already
			read the data, for example with a call to the <command>upload
			data <arg>upload name</arg></command> command.
      </para>
    </example>
    <example id="file_download">
      <title>File Download</title>
      <para>
			In general setting up a data file for being sent over http is 
			as easy as determining the file's URI and letting Apache's
			do all that is needed. If this approach fits your design all 
			you have to do is to keep the downloadable files somewhere 
			within Apache's DocumentRoot (or in any of the directories 
			Apache has right to access).
      </para>
      <para>
			When a client sends a request for a file, Apache takes
			care of determining the filetype, sends appropriate headers to
			the client and then the file content. The client is responsible
			for deciding how to handle the data accordingly to the 
			"content-type" headers and its internal design. For example
			when browsers give up trying to display a certain "content-type"
			they display a download dialog box asking for directions from
			the user. 
      </para>
      <para>
	Rivet can help if you have more sofisticated needs.  For
	instance you may be developing an application that uses
	webpages to collect input data. This information might be
	passed on to scripts or programs for processing. 
	In this case a real file representing the
	data doesn't exist and the content is generated on demand 
	by the server. 
	In other circumstances you may need to dynamically inhibit 
	the download of specific files and hide them away, 
	Your scripts may expunge from the pages
	every link to these files (your pages are dynamic, aren't
	they?) and move them out of way, but it looks like a
	cumbersome solution.
      </para>
      <para>
	Putting Tcl and Rivet in charge of the whole download
	mechanism helps in building cleaner and safer approaches to
	the download problem.
      </para>
      <para>
	In this example a procedure checks for the existence of a
	parameter passed in by the browser. The parameter is the name
	(without extension) of a pdf file.  
	Pdf files are stored in a directory whose path is
	in the <command>pdf_repository</command> variable.
      </para> 
      <para>
	This code is reported as an example of how to control 
	the protocol using the <command>headers</command> command.
      </para>
      <programlisting>&download.tcl;</programlisting>
      <para>
	Before the pdf is sent the procedure sets the
	<constant>Content-Type</constant>, 
	<constant>Content-Disposition</constant>,
	<constant>Content-Description</constant> and
	<constant>Content-Length</constant> headers to inform
	the client about the file type, name and size. Notice that in
	order to set the <constant>Content-Type</constant> header Rivet 
	uses a specialiezed form of the <command>headers</command> 
	command. Headers must be sent before data gets sent down the 
	output channel. Messing with this prescription causes an error 
	to be raised (in fact the protocol itself is been violated)
      </para>
      <para>
	More information about the meaning of the mime headers in the
	http context can be found at 
	<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/Protocols/rfc2616/rfc2616.html"/>
      </para>
    </example>
    <example id="ajax_xml_messaging">
      <title>XML Messages and Ajax</title>
      <para>
	The <command>headers</command> command is crucial for generating 
	XML messages that have to be understood by JavaScript code used 
	in Ajax applications. 
      </para>
      <para>
	    Ajax is a web programming technique that heavily relies on the abilty of a web browser to run in backround
	    JavaScript functions. JavaScript functions can be run as callbacks of events generated by a user interaction 
	    but they can also react to other I/O events, for example network events. 
	    Modern browsers endow JavaScript with the ability to build http GET/POST requests to be sent to a remote
	    webserver. Generally these requests refer to scripts (e.g. Tcl scripts run by Rivet) which inherit as 
	    variables the arguments encoded in the request. 
	    The output produced by these scripts is sent back to the browser where callbacks functions extract 
	    information and hand it down to functions that directly manipulate a page's DOM.
	    Therefore through Ajax becomes possible to build web applications that are more responsive and flexible: 
	    instead of going through the cycle of request-generation-transfer-display 
	    of a whole page, Ajax scripts request from a webserver only the essential data to be displayed.
	    Ajax emphasizes the requirement of separation between data and user interface, saves 
	    the server from sending over the same html code and graphics if only a fraction of a page has to be 
	    updated, allows the programmer to design flexible solutions for complex forms and makes possible
	    to find new innovative approaches to simple problems (e.g. Google tips that show up as you type in
	    a query). A downside of this approach is the large number of complexities, subtleties and incompatibilities 
	    that still exist in the way different versions of popular browsers handle the DOM elements of a page.
      </para>
      <para>
	    JavaScript can handle the communication between client and server through an instance of a 
	    specialized object. For quite a long time 2 approaches existed, the non-IE world (Firefox,Safari,Opera...) 
	    used the XMLHttpRequest class to create this object, whereas IE (before IE7) used the ActiveXObject class.
	    With the release of IE7 Microsoft introduced native support for XMLHttpRequest class objects thus enabling
	    programmers with a unique method for the development of dynamic pages. 
	</para>
	<para>
	    By creating an instance of this class a POST or GET request can be sent to the server and the response is 
	    stored in a property ('returnedText') of the communication object. It's become widely customary to encode 
	    these responses in XML messages. You can invent your own message structure (either based on XML or anything 
	    else), but one has to be aware that if the http headers are properly set and the message returned to the 
	    client is a well formed XML fragment, also the property XMLResponse is assigned with a reference to an object 
	    that represents the DOM of the XML response. By means of the XML W3C DOM interface the programmer can easily
	    manipulate the data embedded in the XML message.
	</para>
	<para>
	    In this example a Rivet script initializes an array with the essential data regarding a few of the major 
	    composers of the european music. This array plays the role of a database. The script sends back to the 
	    client two types of responses: a catalog of the composers or a single record of a composer.
	</para>
	<programlisting>&rivet_web_service.tcl;</programlisting>
	<para>
	    For sake of brevity the JavaScript and HTML will not listed here. They can be downloaded (along with the Tcl 
	    script) stored in the <ulink url="http://people.apache.org/~mxmanghi/rivet-ajax.tar.gz">rivet-ajax.tar.gz</ulink> archive. 
	    By simply opening this tar archive in a directory accessible 
	    by your apache server and pointing your browser to the rivetService.html page you should see a page with a 
	    drop-down list. Every time a different name is picked from the list a new query is sent and logged in the 
	    apache access.log file, even though the html is never reloaded.
	</para>
    </example>
    <example id="calendar">
	<title>A Calendar Utility</title>
	<para>
	    Rivet comes with a <emphasis>Calendar</emphasis> package that provides classes for printing 
	    calendar tables in various forms.	
	</para>
	<para>
		The <emphasis>HtmlCalendar</emphasis> class prints a calendar table in a similar form the Unix 
		program 'cal' does. Example: the following code
		<programlisting>package require Calendar

proc ::cal_cell_attributes { day month year weekday } {
    if {$weekday == 3} {
        return [list class curr_wkday]
    }
}

set htmlc [HtmlCalendar #auto]
set html_txt [$htmlc emit -container {table class calendar} -current_weekday 3 \
                          -cell_function cal_cell_attributes ]
puts $html_txt
</programlisting>

	    with some CSS styling would print
	 </para>
	 <para>
		<graphic fileref="images/calendar.png" />
	 </para>
  </example>
</section>
