  <section id="help">
    <title>Resources - How to Get Help</title>

    <section>
      <title>Mailing Lists</title>
      <para>
	The Rivet mailing list is the first place you should turn for
	help. If you haven't found the solution to your problem in the documentation  
	or you have a question, idea, or comment about the Rivet code itself send email to
	<email>rivet-dev@tcl.apache.org</email>. To subscribe to the list, post email to
	<email>rivet-dev-subscribe@tcl.apache.org</email>.
      </para>
      <para>
	The mailing list archives are available at <ulink
	  url="http://mail-archives.apache.org/mod_mbox/tcl-rivet-dev/" />
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Newsgroup</title>
      <para>
	The <ulink url="news:comp.lang.tcl"/> newsgroup is a good
	place to ask about Tcl questions in general.  Rivet developers
	also follow the newsgroup, but it's best to ask Rivet-specific
	questions on the Rivet list.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="websites">
      <title>Web Sites</title>

      <para>
	There are several web sites that cover Apache and Tcl
	extensively.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <ulink url="http://tcl.apache.org"/> is the home for the
	    Apache Tcl project.  Go there for the latest versions of
	    our software (if you aren't reading these pages off of the
	    site!).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/"/> is the first
	    place to go for questions about the Apache web server.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <ulink url="http://www.tcl.tk"/> is the canonical site
	    for Tcl information.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <ulink url="http://wiki.tcl.tk"/> is the Tcl'ers Wiki, a
	    free-form place to search for answers and ask for help.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bug Tracking System</title>

      <para>
	Apache Rivet uses the Apache Bug Tracking system at <ulink
	  url="http://issues.apache.org/bugzilla/"></ulink>.  Here,
	you can report problems, or check and see if existing issues
	are already known and being dealt with.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>IRC</title>

      <para>
        Occasionally, someone from the Rivet team is on IRC at
        irc.freenode.net, channel #tcl.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Editing Rivet Template Files</title>
      <para>
	Rivet makes available code for two popular editors,
	<application>emacs</application> and
	<application>vim</application> to facilitate the editing of
	Rivet template files.  The key concept is that the editor is
	aware of the &lt;? and ?&gt; tags and switches back and forth
	between Tcl and HTML modes as the cursor moves.  These files,
	<filename>two-mode-mode.el</filename> and
	<filename>rvt.vim</filename> are available in the
	<filename>contrib/</filename> directory.
      </para>
    </section>


  </section>


