<section id="installation">
    <title>Apache Rivet Installation</title>
    <procedure>
      <step>
	<title>Check Dependencies</title>
	<para>
	  To install Rivet, you will need Tcl 8.4 or greater and
	  Apache 1.3.xx.  It is known to run on Linux, FreeBSD,
	  OpenBSD, and Solaris and HPUX.  Windows NT is also possible
	  - please see the directions in the distribution.  Note that
	  Rivet does not currently work with Apache 2.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<title>Get Rivet</title>
	<para>
	  Download the sources at <ulink
	    url="http://tcl.apache.org/rivet/download"/>.  Currently
	  the only way to obtain Rivet.  In the future, we hope to
	  have a FreeBSD port, Debian package, RPM's, and windows
	  binaries.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step performance="required">
	<title>Install Tcl</title>
	<para>
	  If you don't have Tcl already, you need it!  If you already
	  have it, you should just be able to use your system Tcl as
	  long as it is recent.  You can tell Rivet where Tcl is via
	  the <option>-with-tclconfig</option> option to
	  <command>configure.tcl</command> (see below).</para>
      </step>
      <step performance="optional">
	<title>Get and Install Apache Sources</title>
	<para>
          Rivet needs some Apache include (.h) files in order to
	  build.  The easiest way to get them is to download the
	  source code of the Apache web server, although some systems
	  (Debian GNU/Linux for example) make it possible to install
	  only the headers and other development files.  If you intend
	  to build Rivet statically (compiled into the Apache web
	  server instead of loaded dynamically), you definitely need
	  the sources.  We recommend that you build Rivet as a
	  loadable shared library, for maximum flexibility, meaning
	  that you also build Apache to be able to load modules.
	  Other than that, the default Apache install is fine.  We
	  will tell Rivet where it is located via the
	  <option>-with-apxs</option> option to
	  <command>configure.tcl</command> (see below).
	</para>
	<para>
          The source code for the Apache web server may be found by
          following the links here: <ulink
          url="http://httpd.apache.org/"/>.
	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<title>Uncompress Sources</title>
	<para>
	  We will assume that you have Apache installed at this point.
	  You must uncompress the Rivet sources in the directory where you
	  wish to compile them.

	  <programlisting>gunzip tcl-rivet-X.X.X.tar.gz
tar -xvf tcl-rivet-X.X.X.tar.gz</programlisting>

	</para>
      </step>
      <step>
	<title>Building Rivet</title>
	<substeps>
	  <step>
	    <para>
	      On Linux or Unix systems, Rivet uses the standard
	      ./configure ; make ; make install technique.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      There are several options to configure that might be useful
	      or necessary:
	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>--with-tcl</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      This points to the directory where the
		      <filename>tclConfig.sh</filename> file is located.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>--with-tclsh</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>This points to the location of the
		      <filename>tclsh</filename> executable.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>--with-apxs</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>The location of the <filename>apxs</filename>
		      program that provides information about the
		      configuration and compilation of Apache modules.</para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>
	    </para>

	<programlisting>cd src/
./configure --with-tcl=/usr/lib/tcl8.4/ --with-tclsh=/usr/bin/tclsh8.4 \
	    --with-apxs=/usr/bin/apxs
</programlisting>

	  </step>
	  <step>
	    <title>Run make</title>
	    <para>
	      At this point, you are ready to run make, which should
	      run to completion without any errors (a warning or two
	      is ok, generally).
	    </para>
	  </step>
	  <step>
	    <title>Install</title>
	    <para>
	      Now, you are ready to run the <command>make
		install</command> to install the resulting files.
		This should copy the shared object (like
		<filename>mod_rivet.so</filename>, if one was
		successfully created, into Apache's
		<filename>libexec</filename> directory, as well as
		install some support scripts and various code.
	    </para>
	  </step>
	</substeps>
      </step>
      <step>
	<title>Apache Configuration Files</title>
	<para>
	  Rivet is relatively easy to configure - we start off by
	  adding the module itself:
	</para>

	<programlisting>LoadModule rivet_module	<replaceable>/usr/lib/apache/1.3/mod_rivet.so</replaceable></programlisting>

	<para>
	  This tells Apache to load the Rivet shared object, wherever
	  it happens to reside on your file system.  Now we have to
	  tell Apache what kind of files are "Rivet" files and how to
	  process them:
	</para>

	<programlisting>AddType application/x-httpd-rivet .rvt
AddType application/x-rivet-tcl .tcl</programlisting>

	<para>
	  These tell Apache to process files with the
	  <filename>.rvt</filename> and <filename>.tcl</filename>
	  extensions as Rivet files.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The characters encoding can be changed using the <command>header type</command> command,
	  but if you want to change the default charset for the whole site or directory hierarchy  
	  a new charset can be embedded in a AddType line in a way similar to the html pages encoding.
	</para>
	<programlisting>AddType 'application/x-httpd-rivet;charset=utf-8' rvt</programlisting>
	<para>
	   Pages which this configuration applies to send back to the client
	   a <command>Content-Type:'text/html;charset=utf-8'</command> header.
	</para>
	<para>You may also wish to use Rivet files as index files for
	directories.  In that case, you would do the following:</para>
	<programlisting>DirectoryIndex index.html index.htm index.shtml index.cgi index.tcl index.rvt</programlisting>
	<para>
	  For other directives that Rivet provides for Apache
	  configuration, please see <xref linkend="directives"/>.
	</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
</section>

